Finding Aid for James E. Harbour papers, 1977-2009
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
James E. Harbour papers 1977-2009
Harbour, James E.
3 linear feet
2012132 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of James E. Harbour (donor no. 10794 ) and came to the library in June 2012.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
James E. Harbour is a recognized automotive industry analyst. Early in his career, he worked in the automotive industry as a manager and director in the engineering and financial disciplines at Ford Motor Company and Chrysler Corporation. In 1980, he formed Harbour and Associates, Inc., a consulting firm designed to assist manufacturing companies improve their overall competitiveness. The firm dedicated itself to helping manufacturers develop a strategic focus where the design, product, and manufacturing engineering functions focused on continuous improvement of product quality and efficiency. The firm worked directly with automotive companies throughout the world and expanded its scope to assist companies in industries such as pharmaceuticals, consumer products, electrical components, furniture, and paper products as they study and apply improvement methods.
Harbour and his team created the first Harbour Report, a study of manufacturing performance at original equipment manufacturers (OEMs) in 1980. The report was updated in 1989 and became an annual publication in 1993. The Harbour Report has driven improvements in manufacturing performance for the OEMs over the past three decades. Recognized throughout the automotive industry, the report is read by thousands of automotive OEMs, suppliers, financial analysts, and media each year.
In 2009, he released his autobiography, Factory Man: How Jim Harbour discovered Toyota's quality and productivity methods and helped the U.S. auto industry get competitive, written with James V. Higgins and published by the Society of Manufacturing Engineers (SME).
The Harbour collection concerns his work as an analyst of the automobile industry. In addition to copies of The Harbour Report, the collection includes newspaper and magazine articles written by Harbour or containing references to him, and files pertaining to his participation at automobile related conferences. Also of interest are various promotional and related materials surrounding the publication of his book Factory Man.
Subjects:
Harbour, James E.; Automobile industry and trade--United States.; Automobile journalists--United States.
- Topical files
  - Analysis of the Japanese Landed Cost Advantage for the Manufacture of Subcompact Cars, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Auto Employment Study, 1979 and 1992 (Box 1)
  - Auto Workforce Study, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Auto Workforce Analysis: Workers per Million Vehicles Produced 1979 vs. 1995 (Box 1)
  - Auto Workforce, December 31, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Automotive Competitive Challenges; Going Beyond Lean (Harbour-Felax Group) (Box 1)
  - Automotive -- In-house sourcing (Box 1)
  - Biographical -- personnel appointment notices (Box 1)
  - Biographical --Fast Company, magazine article about Harbour (Box 1)
  - General Motors articles (Box 1)
  - General Motors competitive studies (Box 1)
  - General Motors Metal Stamping press release, October 1998 (Box 1)
    (include mention of Harbour Report)
  - Quotations of others about statements of Harbour (Box 1)
  - Vendor tooling study: "Vendor Tooling: The Not so Missing Link" 2009 (Box 1)
  - Wagoner, Rick, Jr., correspondence with, 2004-2005 (Box 1)
- Harbour family members
  - Laurie Harbour, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Ron Harbour, article about (Box 1)
  - Ken Harbour, article on quality (Box 1)
- Conferences
  - Auto News World Congress, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Japanese Auto Industry Conference, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Automobile Production Conference, 1992 (Box 1)
  - Schafer Hydroforming Congress, 1997 (Box 1)
  - APMA Canada Auto Parts Manufacturing Association, 1998 (Box 1)
  - Letters received following his participation at various meetings, 1983-1994 (Box 1)
- Factory Man
  - Reviews, articles, press releases, interviews, 40 folders in 1 expandable folder (Box 1)
  - Power Point presentation to the Society of Manufacturing Engineers, February 2009, 1 binder (Box 1)
  - Draft of book (Microsoft Word); power-point presentation about book, 4 CD-Rs (Box 1)
- Articles written by Harbour or containing references to him
  - Newspaper clippings and magazine articles, 1977-2009, 1 binder and 10 folders in 1 expandable folder (Box 2)
- Harbour Report
  - The Harbour Report: A Decade Later, Competitive Assessment of the North American Automobile Industry 1979-1989 (Box 2)
  - The Harbour Report: Competitive Assessment of the North American Automobile Industry 1989-1992 (Box 2)
  - The Original Harbour Report 1980, 1981 (Second Edition) (Box 2)
  - The Harbour Report, Manufacturing Analysis, Company by Company, Plant by Plant, Europe, 1995-1996 and 1999-2005, 9 issues (Box 3)
  - The Harbour Report, Manufacturing Analysis, Company by Company, Plant by Plant, North America, 2000-2005 and 2007, 7 issues (Box 3)
  - Promotional brochure for 2004 report (Box 3)